I still remember the day in school
مازلت اذكر اليوم الذي قالت لي فيه
when our teacher told us
مدرستي في المدرسة
that the world population had become
ان العالم قد غدا عدد سكانه
three billion people,
3 مليارات نسمة
and that was in 1960.
في عام 1960
I'm going to talk now about
وسوف اتحدث الآن
how world population has changed from that year
كيف تغير ذلك الرقم منذ ذلك العام
and into the future,
وحتى المستقبل القادم
but I will not use digital technology,
ولكني لن استخدم التقنيات الحديثة
as I've done during my first five TEDTalks.
كما فعلت في احاديثي الخامسة السابقة في مؤتمر تيد
Instead, I have progressed,
لانني تطورت اكثر
and I am, today, launching
وانا اليوم اطلق
a brand new analog teaching technology
طريقة جديدة للتعليم
that I picked up from IKEA:
استعرتها من " ايكيا " - سلسلة محال مفروشات -
this box.
هي هذا الصندوق
This box contains one billion people.
هذا الصندوق يحوي في داخله مليار نسمة
And our teacher told us
وقد اخبرتنا مدرستي
that the industrialized world, 1960,
ان العالم الصناعي في عام 1960
had one billion people.
كان عدده مليار نسمة
In the developing world, she said,
اما العالم النامي فقد قالت لي ان عدده
they had two billion people.
2 مليار نسمة
And they lived away then.
وقد كانوا يعيشون بعيدا جدا عن العالم الصناعي
There was a big gap between
فقد كان هنالك فرق كبير في مستوى معيشة كلا العالمين
the one billion in the industrialized world
بين الواحد مليار في العالم الصناعي
and the two billion in the developing world.
وبين الاثنين مليار في العالم النامي
In the industrialized world,
ففي العالم الصناعي
people were healthy,
كان الناس بصحة جيدة
educated, rich,
متعلمون .. اغنياء
and they had small families.
لديهم عائلات صغيرة
And their aspiration
وكان طموحهم آنذاك
was to buy a car.
شراء سيارة
And in 1960, all Swedes were saving
ففي عام 1960 كان معظم السويديون يوفرون اموالهم
to try to buy a Volvo like this.
لشراء سيارة فولفو كهذه
This was the economic level at which Sweden was.
فقد كان هذا معيار الغنى آنذاك في السويد
But in contrast to this,
وعلى النقيض من هذا
in the developing world, far away,
كان العالم النامي بعيدا جدا عن هذا المستوى
the aspiration of the average family there
فقد كان طموح العائلات هناك
was to have food for the day.
توفير لقمة العيش ليوم واحد فحسب
They were saving
وكانوا يوفرون الاموال
to be able to buy a pair of shoes.
لكي يتمكنوا من شراء زوج من الاحذية !
There was an enormous gap in the world
لقد كان هنالك فارق كبير جدا بين العالمين
when I grew up.
وعندما كبرت
And this gap between the West and the rest
كانت تلك الفجوة قد ترسخت
has created a mindset of the world,
مما طرح مصطلحين لغويين
which we still use linguistically
يتم استخدامهما حتى يومنا هذا
when we talk about "the West"
هما العالم الغربي
and "the Developing World."
والعالم النامي
But the world has changed,
ولكن العالم تغير
and it's overdue to upgrade that mindset
ليغير تلك الصورة التي سادت طيلة ذلك الوقت
and that taxonomy of the world, and to understand it.
ويغير تصنيف العالم .. ولفهم ذلك التغير
And that's what I'm going to show you,
سوف اريكم هذا العرض ..
because since 1960
منذ عام 1960
what has happened in the world up to 2010
وحتى عام 2010 .. الذي حدث للعالم هو
is that a staggering
امرٌ مدهش
four billion people
فقد ازداد عدد سكان العالم 4 مليارات
have been added to the world population.
ليغدوا 7 مليارات نسمة
Just look how many.
انظروا كم هذا العدد كبير
The world population has doubled
لقد تضاعف عدد السكان
since I went to school.
منذ ذلك اليوم الذي كنت فيه في المدرسة
And of course, there's been economic growth in the West.
وبالطبع .. قد نمى الاقتصاد في الغرب
A lot of companies have happened to grow the economy,
وقد استطاعت الشركات ان تنمي الاقتصاد ككل
so the Western population moved over to here.
ليصبح العالم الغربي هنا على هذا المكان في الطاولة
And now their aspiration is not only to have a car.
وقد تغير طموح افراد هذا العالم من شراء سيارة
Now they want to have a holiday on a very remote destination
الى قضاء عطلات خارج القارة .. او خارج حدود الوطن
and they want to fly.
فقد أرادوا الطيران
So this is where they are today.
اذا هذا هو وضعنا الحالي
And the most successful of the developing countries,
وقد استطاعت الدول النامية الناجحة
they have moved on, you know,
التحرك الى هذا الموقع .. كما ترون
and they have become emerging economies, we call them.
فقد غدت تلك الاقتصاديات اقتصاديات ناشئة، كما نسميها
They are now buying cars.
وقد اصبح طموح سكانها شراء سيارات
And what happened a month ago
والذي حدث منذ شهر تحديدا
was that the Chinese company, Geely,
ان شركة صينية تدعى " جيلي " لصناعة السيارات
they acquired the Volvo company,
قامت بالإستحواذ على شركة " فولفو "
and then finally the Swedes understood that
وعندها فقط استطاع السويديون ان يدركوا
something big had happened in the world.
ان هنالك تغير كبير في العالم يحدث
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So there they are.
إذا ها هم ..
And the tragedy is that the two billion over here
ولكن المأساة هي ان الاثنين مليار هنا
that is struggling for food and shoes,
مازلوا يصارعون للحصول على الطعام والاحذية
they are still almost as poor
وقد بقوا في مكانهم كالأكثر فقراً
as they were 50 years ago.
كما كانوا منذ 50 عام
The new thing is that
والشيء الجديد
we have the biggest pile of billions, the three billions here,
هو هذه المليارات الثالث من السكان
which are also becoming emerging economies,
والتي بدات ايضا اقتصادياتها بالنمو
because they are quite healthy, relatively well-educated,
لانها غدت أكثر صحة .. واكثر تعليما - نسبيا - لما كانت عليه
and they already also have two to three children
وقد اصبحوا ينجبوا طفلين او ثلاث
per woman, as those [richer also] have.
لكل إمراة .. وقد اصبح ..
And their aspiration now
طموحهم
is, of course, to buy a bicycle,
هو بالتاكيد .. شراء عجلة هوائية
and then later on they would like to have a motorbike also.
ومن ثم قد يركبون درجات نارية
But this is the world
وهذا هو العالم
we have today,
الذي نقطن فيه اليوم
no longer any gap.
لم يعد هناك فروق طبقية كبيرة بين الطبقات
But the distance from the poorest here, the very poorest,
ولكن المسافة بقيت بين الفقراء .. اقصد الاكثر فقرا
to the very richest over here is wider than ever.
كبيرة جدا .. او اكبر مما كانت عليه سابقا
But there is a continuous world
ولكن هنالك نوع من التسلسل في العالم
from walking, biking,
من بيئات تتنقل على الاقدام .. الى العجلات الهوائية
driving, flying --
الى السيارات .. الى الطائرات
there are people on all levels,
اي هنالك أُناس على جميع المستويات
and most people tend to be somewhere in the middle.
ومعظم الناس تقطن في الطبقة الوسطى
This is the new world we have today
وهذا هو عالمنا اليوم
in 2010.
عالم 2010
And what will happen in the future?
ولكن مالذي سيحدث في المستقبل
Well, I'm going to project
سوف احدثكم عن ماذا سيحدث
into 2050.
عام 2050
I was in Shanghai recently,
لقد كنت في شانغهاي مؤخرا
and I listened to what's happening in China,
وكنت استمع الى ما يحدث في الصين
and it's pretty sure that they will catch up,
وانا متاكد جدا انهم سيلحقون الركب
just as Japan did.
كما فعلت اليابان من قبل
All the projections [say that] this one [billion] will [only] grow with
تشير جميع التوقعات ان هذا الجزء من العالم
one to two or three percent.
سوف ينمو بمقدار 2-3%
[But this second] grows with seven, eight percent, and then they will end up here.
بينما سوف ينمو هذا الجزء 7-8% لكي يصلوا الى هنا
They will start flying.
وسوف يبدأون بالطيران
And these
وهذه الفئة
lower or middle income countries, the emerging income countries,
ذات الاقتصاديات المنخفضة .. والمتوسطة .. والناشئة
they will also forge forwards economically.
سوف تتحرك الى الاقتصاديات المتطورة
And if,
واذا
but only if,
فقط اذا
we invest in the right green technology --
استطعنا ان نستثمر في التكنولوجيا البيئية الخضراء المناسبة
so that we can avoid severe climate change,
بحيث يمكننا تفادي اخطار الاحتباس الحراري و التغير المناخي
and energy can still be relatively cheap --
وعندما تصبح كلفة الطاقة منخفضة نسبيا
then they will move all the way up here.
سوف تتحرك هذه الفئة الى الاعلى هنا
And they will start to buy
وسوف يبدأون بشراء
electric cars.
سيارات كهربائية
This is what we will find there.
هذا ما ستؤول اليه الامور
So what about the poorest two billion?
ولكن ماذا عن الاثنين مليار من الفقراء
What about the poorest two billion here?
ماذا عن هؤلاء الاثنين مليار من الفقراء
Will they move on?
هل سيتغير وضعهم ؟
Well, here population [growth] comes in
حسنا من هنا ستاتي الزيادة السكانية
because there [among emerging economies] we already have two to three children per woman,
لان هنا في تلك المنطقة .. يملك ذلك العالم معدل انجاب هو طفلين او ثلاث لكل امراة
family planning is widely used,
لان هنالك تحديد للنسل يتم استخدامه على نطاق واسع
and population growth is coming to an end.
والنمو السكاني في تلك المنطقة سوف يستقر
Here [among the poorest], population is growing.
بينما هنا .. السكان تنمو
So these [poorest] two billion will, in the next decades,
لذا سوف يصبح الاثنان مليار هنا في العقود القادمة
increase to three billion,
3 مليارات
and they will thereafter
ومن ثم
increase to four billion.
الى 4 مليارات
There is nothing --
ولا يوجد شيء
but a nuclear war of a kind we've never seen --
سوى حرب نووية يمكنها ان تحول
that can stop this [growth] from happening.
دون حدوث ذلك
Because we already have this [growth] in process.
لانهم ماضون على هذا النسق الآن
But if, and only if,
ولكن فقط .. اذا وفقط اذا
[the poorest] get out of poverty,
تم انتشالهم من الفقر
they get education, they get improved child survival,
وتم رفع مستوى التعليم لديهم .. ورفع العمر الافتراضي للطفل لديهم
they can buy a bicycle and a cell phone and come [to live] here,
بيحث يمكنهم شراء دراجات هوائية وهواتف محمولة .. سوف تنتقل هذه الفئة الى هنا
then population growth
وسوف يتوقف النمو السكاني
will stop in 2050.
بحلول عام 2050
We cannot have people on this level
لانه لايمكننا الابقاء على هذه الناس عند هذا المستوى
looking for food and shoes
وهم في حالة بحث دائم عن الطعام والاحذية
because then we get continued population growth.
لانه بدون هذا سوف تستمر الزيادة السكانية لديهم
And let me show you why
ودعوني اريكم لماذا
by converting back to the old-time
باستخدام الطريقة السابقة
digital technology.
طريقة التحليل الرقمي
Here I have on the screen
الذي لدي على هذه الشاشة
my country bubbles.
دوائر تعبر عن الدول
Every bubble is a country. The size is population.
كل دائرة من هذه هي دولة .. وحجمها مرتبط بعدد سكان تلك الدولة
The colors show the continent.
والالوان توضح القارات التي تنتمي لها هذه الدولة
The yellow on there is the Americas;
الدوائر الصفراء تعبر عن الامريكيتين
dark blue is Africa; brown is Europe;
والزرقاء الداكنة افريقيا .. والبنية اوروبا
green is the Middle East
والخضراء .. دول الشرق المتوسط
and this light blue is South Asia.
والزرقاء الفاتحة ..دول جنوب اسيا
That's India and this is China. Size is population.
وهذه الهند .. وهذه الصين .. الحجم يعبر عن عدد السكان
Here I have children per woman:
وعلى هذا المحور لدي عدد الاطفال لكي امراة
two children, four children, six children, eight children --
طفلين .. اربعة اطفال .. ستة اطفال .. تسعة اطفال
big families, small families.
هنا عائلات كبيرة .. وهنا عائلات صغيرة
The year is 1960.
العام هو 1960
And down here, child survival,
وهنا على هذا المحور معدل بقاء الطفل على قيد الحياة
the percentage of children surviving childhood
تشير النسبة الى احتمال بقاء الطفل على قيد الحياة
up to starting school:
حتى بلوغه عامه الدراسي الاول
60 percent, 70 percent, 80 percent, 90,
60-70-80-90 %
and almost 100 percent, as we have today
وهنا تكاد تصل الى 100%
in the wealthiest and healthiest countries.
في الدول الاكثر ثروة ..و صحة
But look, this is the world my teacher talked about in 1960:
انظروا .. هذا هو العالم الذي اشارت اليه مدرستي آنذاك في عام 1960
one billion Western world here --
مليار شخص في العالم الغربي
high child-survival, small families --
بمعدل بقاء مرتفع .. واسر صغيرة
and all the rest,
وباقي الدول
the rainbow of developing countries,
النامية - ذات الدوائر الملونة -
with very large families
بعائلات كبيرة
and poor child survival.
وبمعدل بقاء منخفض
What has happened? I start the world. Here we go.
ومالذي حدث على مدى هذه الفترة .. سوف اسير بالزمن .. ها نحن ننطلق
Can you see, as the years pass by, child survival is increasing?
هل ترون كيفية تغير الامور مع الزمن .. كيفية ارتفاع معدل بقاء الاطفال على قيد الحياة
They get soap, hygiene, education,
فقد وصلهم الصابون .. وارتفعت الصحة .. والتعليم
vaccination, penicillin
والبنسلين .. واللقاحات
and then family planning. Family size is decreasing.
ومن ثم تحديد النسل .. وبداية الحد من اعداد الاسر
[When] they get up to 90-percent child survival, then families decrease,
حتى وصلت الى نسبة بقاء 90% .. ومن ثم انخفضت ايضا اعداد الاسر
and most of the Arab countries in the Middle East
وهنا الدول العربية في الشرق الاوسط
is falling down there [to small families].
تهبط الى هذا المستوى
Look, Bangladesh catching up with India.
انظروا الى بنغلادش كيف تلاحق الهند
The whole emerging world
انظروا الى الاقتصاديات الناشئة
joins the Western world
كيف انضمت الى ركب الدول الغربية
with good child survival
بمعدل بقاء مرتفع
and small family size,
وباسر صغيرة العدد
but we still have the poorest billion.
ولكن مازال المليارين الفقيرين هنا
Can you see the poorest billion,
هل يمكنكم ان تروا المليارين الفقيرين
those [two] boxes I had over here?
هذه هي التي عبرت عنها بالصناديق من قبل
They are still up here.
مازالوا هنا
And they still have a child survival
ومازالت نسبة بقاء الطفل لديهم
of only 70 to 80 percent,
%70-80
meaning that if you have six children born,
اي ان كان لديك 6 اطفال هناك
there will be at least four who survive
فان 4 منهم سوف يعيشون
to the next generation.
حتى يروا الجيل القادم
And the population will double in one generation.
وسوف تتضاعف اعدادهم خلال جيل واحد
So the only way
لذا الطريقة الوحيدة
of really getting world population [growth] to stop
لكي نوقف هذا النمو السكاني المطرد
is to continue to improve child survival
او ان نستمر بتحسين معدل بقاء الاطفال على قيد الحياة بعد الولادة
to 90 percent.
حتى تصل الى 90%
That's why investments by Gates Foundation,
وهذا هو سبب استثمار مؤسسة " جيتس "
UNICEF and aid organizations,
واليونسيف والمعونات الدولية
together with national government in the poorest countries,
مع المؤسسات الوطنية في الدول الفقيرة
are so good;
هي الافضل على الاطلاق
because they are actually
لانها تعمل على استهداف هذه المشكلة
helping us to reach
لكي تساعدنا على الحصول
a sustainable population size of the world.
على عالم به عدد سكان مستقر
We can stop at nine billion if we do the right things.
نعم .. يمكننا التوقف عند عدد 9 مليار نسمة ان قمنا بالتصرفات الصحيحة
Child survival is the new green.
اليوم معدل بقاء الاطفال هو الهدف الجديد
It's only by child survival
ان فقط رفع ذلك المعدل
that we will stop population growth.
سوف يوقف النمو السكاني المطرد
And will it happen?
وهل سيحدث ذلك ؟
Well, I'm not an optimist,
انا لست متفائلا جدا
neither am I a pessimist.
ولست ايضا متشائما جدا
I'm a very serious "possibilist."
انا شخص جدي .. وواقعي وادرس الاحتمالات
It's a new category where we take emotion apart,
انها واقعية جديدة .. فعندما نحيد العواطف
and we just work analytically with the world.
ونعمل فقط مع الحقائق التي تخص عالمنا ونحللها
It can be done.
يمكننا ان ننجز ذلك
We can have a much more just world.
يمكننا ان نحصل على عالم أكثر عدلاً
With green technology
لديه تكنولوجيا بيئية
and with investments to alleviate poverty,
وباستثمارات تحد من الفقر
and global governance,
وبسياسات عالمية
the world can become like this.
ويمكن ان يغدو عالمنا كهذا
And look at the position of the old West.
انظروا الى موقع الدول الغريبة القديمة
Remember when this blue box was all alone,
تذكروا من ذي قبل كان هذا الصندوق الازرق لوحده
leading the world, living its own life.
يقود العالم .. ويعيش حياته بتفرد دون غيره
This will not happen [again].
حسناً .. هذا لن يحدث بعد اليوم
The role of the old West in the new world
لقد اصبح دول الدول الغربية في العالم الجديد
is to become the foundation
هو دور الاساس للمباني
of the modern world --
في هذا العالم الحديث
nothing more, nothing less.
لا اكثر ولا اقل
But it's a very important role.
وهو دور هام جدا
Do it well and get used to it.
قوموا به .. واعتادوا عليه
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)